[music]
Hello everyone and welcome back. I'm
Ostrus and today we're going to go over
Zimage Turbo. We're going to train it on
AI toolkit. I'm excited. Let's get
started. Z Image Turbo dropped a few
days ago. They're also going to release
Zimage Base, which is the model you
really need to train on, and they're
going to release Zimage Edit. Uh early
on, right when they released Zimage
Turbo, this one, it's an eightstep
distilled model. It can do less than
that. Actually, they say here that they
will be releasing Zimage base, Zimage.
Everyone thought this was going to come
day one or day two. I got super anxious
because on Flux Chanel when this came
out, this is also a turbo model. Um, I
built a training adapter for this early
on so that you could train this in AI
toolkit directly without breaking down
the distillation. This was something I
experimented with for a very long time.
It took a long time to perfect it and
get it just right. And so when Zimage
Turbo came out and they hadn't released
the other models yet, I wanted to train
this because this model is amazing. It
does amazing realism and it's only 6
billion parameters. So, it's small
compared to like flux is 12 billion or
flux 2 is 32 billion. This one's only
six. It's fast. It can do it in eight
steps. So, when you're generating this,
it's super fast, super lightweight. They
didn't release the base yet. Um, and
early on, everyone thought it was going
to be released in a day or two. And then
there was some confusion on their GitHub
repo uh where they were answering a
different question and people thought
that meant that the model was going to
be released by the weekend. But it turns
out what they were talking about is the
prompt upsampler. They said it would be
a little bit on the image base. Luckily
I was already working on an adapter so
we could train this thing. But before we
get into all that I want to give a shout
out to Alibaba. I mean so this is Tong
May. Um, I can't pronounce that, but
it's a subsidiary of Alibaba. It's a
group within Alibaba. And if you don't
know, a lot of the big open models that
have come out, like Apache 2.0,
completely open models with permissible
licenses have come out of this. You can
tell all these. So, you look at Juan
Quinn, they all have, you can tell they
have that same logo. That's the Alibaba
logo. So, it's all from the same
company, but they're just labs within
that company. So, I mean, we owe so much
of the current open-source image
generation and also text generation and
video generation to Alibaba. They're
just doing amazing things in the open
space right now, and I think we really
need to appreciate what all they've done
for us. So, let's get back into this
Zage Turbo. So, you can't train this
directly. It's a distilled model. If you
train it, it'll break down. So, I came
up with a while back a way to do a
training adapter. And here's my Z image
Turbo training adapter. You can go here.
I'll post a link in the description. But
basically how this works when you train
on Zage Turbo. So this is eight step no
CFG. So it doesn't have to do a dual
pass. It's a single pass. This only
takes eight steps of a single pass.
Normally you have to use CFG. So there's
two passes. So it takes twice as long.
This one since it's a distilled model
you do eight steps and you get these
images. This is the base. And I was
training in my musician character. I've
mentioned them a few times. I've posted
pictures a few times. We've done
tutorials a few times, but this is
basically what they look like. Now, when
you train this without the adapter, this
actually starts to break down. You can
see like these weird artifacts
happening. This is after 500 steps. And
you see all this like it's breaking
down. So, the model, general diffusion
models, they want classifier free
guidance and about 20 to 50 steps to
make a good image. You know, that's how
every model that's come out, that's what
you have to do. And so when you're
training it, it's breaking down to try
to do that because we're doing
traditional training here. When they
distill it, they actually do student
teacher so that they'll essentially
shorten the amount of steps it take.
This is a short definition of it, but
that's basically what's going on in the
high level. There's critics now and a
bunch of other things. We've gone from
LCM. There's a lot of different ways to
do this and they've done it a different
way as well, but that's the basic gist.
you're squishing down the steps into
where it can do it in very few steps,
even one step if possible. But when you
start training on that, the model wants
to restore back to its original state of
being a 20 to 50 step model that
requires CFG. And you can tell here,
this is eight steps, no CFG. And so
after 500 steps of training, it it is
learning my character, but it's also
breaking down that distillation. There's
a point like here we probably if we add
a little CFG it would be clearer or if
you do more steps it'd be clearer but as
you continue to train this it would just
break down completely to where you would
need 30 40 steps and you would need
classifier free guidance to make this
look good at all. And so you don't want
to do that with every single lure you
train because you want the turbo. So
that's where the adapter comes in. You
can see it here working. you get nice
crisp clean images without breaking down
the distillation. So you can come here
and read how it works. The basic idea is
I generated a ton of images, a huge data
set with Z image turbo and then we just
train a Laura on that and over time
it'll break down. So it's just breaking
down the distillation but it's not going
to learn anything new. It's not learning
our character. It's not learning any new
information. This is all information
that's inside the model. So when we
train, what we can do is we actually
take this adapter Laura that now has all
the distillation broken down and we
apply it to the model and we train on
top of that. So that way you're
basically training on a model without
distillation. So it's just going to
learn your concept or your character.
After that's done training or when
you're sampling, you remove the training
adapter. So now you remove the dd
distilled Laura and what's left is your
new information on the distilled model.
So you can basically train a Laura on a
turbo model without breaking down the
turbo. It'll allow us to do things like
inference and get great quality in very
few steps while still teaching it
whatever we're trying to teach it.
Teaching it about our character concept
etc. This is a D-D distillation training
adapter. This is how it's going to work.
It's already built in the AI toolkit.
We're ready to go. We're ready to train.
Let's get started. I'll show you how you
can use this and I'll talk about some of
the caveats along the way. You can kind
of see here what's the catch. The basics
is you're not going to do a 5 million
image fine-tune using this adapter. It
just slows down the distillation process
over time. If you train for 20 million
steps, you are going to break down that
distillation. But for 5,000, 10,000,
maybe even 20,000 steps, you're probably
fine on training characters, styles,
things like that. And that's what we're
going to do today. Now, I'm currently in
the process of moving. I would do this
locally. I'm going to do it on RunPod
today because I have a lot of stuff
packed up. I actually didn't have time
to record this video, but it's been
highly requested. And since this is a
new type of training and a new type of
thing, I wanted to make sure I went over
it and explained how this works and the
caveats. That being said, I don't have
my GPUs set up and ready to go. So, I'm
going to use run pod. You can totally do
this locally. It is a small model. 24
gigs of VRAM is fine. Um, less than that
is fine. Uh, I think you could get by
with 16 without doing any real
offloading like block offloading with
RAM torch. I'm going to go ahead and pop
over. I'm going to do a 5090 just for
speed. I'll post a link of how to do
this in RunPod if you want, but I'm
going to blow through it real quick.
All right, so we're up in AI toolkit.
Again, you can do this all locally. Just
go to the repo. There's instructions on
how to install it there. I mean, this
will work. I'm doing it on a 5090 here
just to demonstrate. Let's come over to
data sets. So, I already have a data set
prepped. This is an older one I've done.
Children's drawings. Sounds good. We're
going to add our images. Just going to
drag these.
Now, I'm going to save you guys the
time. I already captioned all these. And
you can just drag captions in the text
files. That works fine. Just drag it
over. And you can tell all my captions
are already here. These are just a bunch
of children's drawings I found on the
internet. Just real simple ones like sun
and, you know, people. Now, how I'm
going to do this one, you can do a
trigger word, and that does seem to help
a lot when you're training. That's one
way to do style. Another way to do style
is to just caption it. So, like for
instance, on this one, we just have a
bear, a pig, a green balloon, an owl
wearing suspenders, a donkey, and a
blurry man with a red shirt standing on
grass. A bunny man with a red shirt
standing on grass. So, I just describe
what it is. as if it's a picture or
whatever. I'm not mentioning it's child
drawing and you know rough crayon
sketch, you know, crude drawing,
anything like that. I'm just acting like
this is the new normal. The new normal
is when someone types in a picture of a
woman, you get this. And when someone
types in an owl, you get this. And a
house looks like this. And so I'm
teaching the model these normal things.
It knows this is how you're going to
render them. Now,
pretty simple. That's how I like to do
style. Some people like trigger words.
Trigger words are good. They do seem to
help sometimes, but I really like it
where it's just you apply the lore and
this is just how it works. So, that's
how I'm doing it today. Let's pop over
to new job. I'm going to go over some
settings real quick. We'll just do Z
image turbo children's drawings. I'm
going to skip trigger word on the
architecture. You can scroll here or you
can just type in We can just type in Z.
There's only one model with a Z in it. I
didn't realize that. That's pretty
impressive. Now, on this, because this
is the Zimage Turbo, we have a training
adapter. Uh, if this is Zimage base,
I'll have that in here when they release
it. Um, and you won't need the training
adapter, but the training adapter is
already built in. You don't have to go
download it. This just pulls it straight
from the repo. And then it tells it
which file name to pull. It's currently
V1. I am working on a V2, just training
it a lot longer so it'll be a little
better. Um, when that comes out, this
will automatically update if you're
doing a new one. If you're cloning an
existing one, you'll need to just
upgrade this to V2 when that comes out.
So, you could do that, but it's not
currently available. So, we have our
training adapter. All this is going to
automatically work in AI toolkit. It'll
merge it in starting out and then it'll
merge it out when you're inferencing.
So, we can still do eight steps. I'm
going to leave all this the same, 3,000
steps on the learning rate. This is 1
Eg4. There have been some people test it
with 2E4 and it exploded the model. So,
I would not go any higher than this.
This seems to be kind of the sweet spot.
But all the defaults are good. Today, I
actually want to use
differential guidance. Uh this is what I
use to actually train the turbo adapter.
Um you can read about it here. It's in
the advanced section. You can see the
basic idea of differential guidance is
normally you're moving your target or
you're moving your current knowledge
closer and closer to your target with
your learning rate. So it's going boom
and it'll jump a little closer, a little
closer, a little closer, but you never
actually get there. So it's just a
little bit at a time and then you just
get the differential becomes less and
less. So you just get smaller and
smaller, you get closer and closer and
you'll never actually hit your target.
And I personally think this is one of
the big problems with training any
neural network. it it generalizes too
much. Like your person's never exactly
like the person you're training or your
concepts never exactly like the concept
you're training. It's kind of a an
averaged out lesser version of that. So
with differential guidance, basically
what we do is we take the difference
between your current knowledge and your
target and we kind of do something
basically like classifier free guidance
works. We subtract the differential, we
amplify the differential and we add it
back. So now your new target is like way
overshot. This isn't quite the same as
just increasing the learning rate.
Increasing the learning rate will get
you from here to here. If you do a
learning rate of one, it'll actually hit
here, but it'll explode the model
because the model can't handle that. But
it will never actually get you beyond
this. It'll just get you closer to the
target faster or destroy the model. With
differential guidance, we're actually
overamplifying the difference. And so
it'll target just a little beyond the
target or maybe right at it. So when you
do your step, you're now coming here.
And your next step now is going to be
back. It's going to overshoot a little
here, here, and it'll work its way to
the target. Just slightly different.
It's just a little thing I came up with.
It may not even function the way I think
it does, but it does seem to work. I'm
going to turn that on. We're just going
to do a guidance skill of three. You
don't have to do this if you don't want.
It's experimental. I like it. I'm
leaving it. We're going to come down. We
have children's drawings selected.
Everything can be the same. We're going
to leave all the resolutions the same.
So when we selected this model turbo, it
automatically set everything. So we have
our sample step set to eight, our
guidance scale set to one. Uh we don't
need to mess with any of that. We're not
going to touch any of this. So we're
going to see what the model knows. We
don't have to add trigger words because
we're adapting it to this is just how it
is now. So, it's going to hopefully
start doing children's art pretty
quickly on. I am going to bump this just
so we can run it out if we need to.
Sometimes these really amplified styles
take a little longer. I don't have to
come back in and restart it cuz I'm
going to be busy packing and stuff while
this is training. But that's it. Let's
go back to the top. I want to go over
how you can get this lower than what I'm
doing today. Uh, first thing, if you
have 24 gigs or more, set this to none.
This won't quantize. It'll be way
faster. Um, you can set this to eight.
Leave both these eight. You can also do
cache text embeddings. U, I'll probably
leave the cache text embeddings on
because there's no reason to keep the
text encoder loaded. This just caches
all your text embeddings and then loads
them up, unloads the text encoder. Um,
but this will save us some VRAM. I'm
going to leave mine on none, so it's
faster. If you have 24 gigs VRAM, do
this. You may be able to get by with
less, but we'll see that in a second.
Other than that, we left everything the
same. We did turn on differential
guidance. To activate this, you just
click this little advanced tab. Not
needed, but I'm doing it. And other than
that, we're all good. So, let's go
create that job. Okay. I'm going to go
ahead and hit play. And when you start
this, it'll go ahead and download all
the models. It's funny that I'm like,
oh, this is only 14 gigabytes. That's
real small. I remember back when you
could do the entire text encoder and
everything in under two with SD1. Now,
if we're like, oh, it's less than 100
gigabytes. That's tiny. Things have
changed in a few years. So, you can see
it's about 4 seconds of iteration. Now,
for this one, we actually, the way I
merge it in is I actually merge in the
adapter Laura. So, you train without
having to have the side chain Laura. And
then when we're generating, we actually
have a side chain of this. So, we're
actually slowing it down pretty
substantially on generation, but you're
getting like 4 seconds in iteration here
on generating these images. It's so
freaking fast. Absolutely incredible.
Let's go look at the samples. Okay, so
this is baseline knowledge and you can
just see here how amazing this little
six billion parameter model is.
Just look at this. I mean, it does photo
realism really good. One of the things
it does struggle with though is style
and text. It's not the best at text, but
it's pretty good. I mean, compared to
SDXL or anything like that, it's light
years ahead on text, but compared to
like Flux 2, it's not as good at text.
But if you like photo realism like I do,
just look at these. I mean, they're
incredible. Amazing detail, all that.
Amazing. I stepped away for one second
and I didn't even get to go over the
training speeds before it had the next
samples. I mean, look at this thing.
1.27 seconds in iteration. 1 second
iteration. We're averaging 1.3 over all
resolutions.
This model's tight and fast. Even with
the training adapter, it's so fast. And
we come over here. Look at our memory
usage. Um 17 gigabytes of VRAM to train
this thing. And we're not quantizing. I
mean, we're training at brain float 16,
Bflat 16, 17 gigs of VRAM. So, if you
quantize this, you get that down even
further. I mean, we're looking at 16 gig
VRAM cards here. We could probably run
this on. If you get it running on
something smaller, share it in the
comments or hop on the Discord, share it
in the config section. Let people know
how you're training this on lower-end
hardware. I really want to know. But,
let's go check out the samples. So,
we're going from there to there. This is
going to take a little bit, but it's
starting to have a trajectory for sure.
Uh, doing a whole style like this where
we're we're basically changing the
entire composition. It might be good to
actually switch it to favor high noise,
but I'm going to leave it where it is.
It's getting there. We got to break up
all of its knowledge cuz everything you
notice none of these look like cartoons
starting out. Like even like the obscure
ones like bears and dogs, it's still
doing realism. Normally, these would be
cartoons in every single model that you
generate because they're not like a real
picture. All right, we are at a little
over 2,000 steps. Uh, I'm gonna come
take a look at samples here.
Okay,
so let's just go down the training run
for this one for instance. As we come
down, ah, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes. Okay,
that's absolutely awesome.
Yeah,
I love the little child art style. I'm
going to have a lot of fun with this
one. Uh some of them don't have it.
I It's kind of doing it. But yeah, some
of this is because we're not using a
trigger word. I'll show you guys how to
bump this and make it hit a little
harder. Yeah, this one's looking good.
This is the bear. Yeah, bear in the
cabin.
It's so good.
I mean, some of them aren't doing it.
Some of them are. It's about 50/50.
Oh, I love it. Okay, let's pause this.
Make sure we're not saving or anything
right now.
I'm going to show you guys on this one.
So, we're even though it's style, we're
technically wanting to adjust the
content of the image. Like the base
layout, the very first high noise steps
of what it starts to build. We don't
want it to build a color image. We want
it to start building a drawing. So, one
of the things you can do here, it's good
to keep this balanced on time step bias.
But for this one, we want to do the high
noise. So, those early time steps, we
want to really, you know, affect the
image of changing all the composition
because this is a drastic change in
composition we're trying to do. So, this
will do mostly the really high noise
areas. So, when you're generating the
first few steps, um, it'll still hit all
of them, but it just has a heavy high
noise bias. Let's update that. Later, we
may go back to balance after we get
everything moved over because we still
want to really focus on those little
like textures of the crayon and all of
that. That just depends on how it's
looking. I'm going to start this back
up. Remember, we are on step 2,250.
All right, next step came in.
All right. So, you can see it was here
and now we're here. So, adjusting that
to a high noise, it really helps rebuild
the composition of the image. We're just
focusing just on that. So, man, all
these,
every single one of them, even the
problem ones are all there. [laughter]
I just love that. I mean, look how much
of a drastic impact it makes. So, we go
here, here, here, here.
Great. Okay, we are at 3,000 steps.
Let's go ahead and give this a stop.
It's typically that's the default
number. I want to be done there. Let's
go look. Okay, I'm going to go over to
samples. All right, here we go. Let's
take a look at these final ones.
It's It's so bad and that makes it so
good.
A woman with red hair playing chess in a
park. a bomb going off in the
background. I like it's just like
simplified versions here. I love it. All
the little chess pieces.
Oh man, it's so good cuz it's so bad. I
mean, that's the thing. We're we're
teaching the model to be worse. Oh, it's
a horse DJ. Look, he he's holding a
little record. Like all the little
things it's doing. His martini glass.
[sighs]
I love it.
Okay, [laughter]
this is the man showing off his cool new
t-shirt at the beach. A shark jumping
out of the water in the background.
I don't see the shark unless that's
supposed to be it. There's one on his
shirt. It's weird how the shirt's like a
real shirt as opposed to a drawing.
Like a mixed medium genius child.
Okay, this is the Bayer building log
cabin. Great. Oh man, see that one's
intricate. This is one that you hang up
on the wall when your kid draws it. A
woman playing guitar on stage singing a
song, laser lights, punk rocker, man.
Even like the little details on the
strings. It's like the details there,
but it's bad the way we want it to be.
All right. Hipster man with a beard
building a chair in a wood shop. God,
love these. I just love these.
This is a sign. Perfect. Oh, [laughter]
I just love this one. The progression.
It comes down and gets worse, worse,
worse. Okay, this is great. I love it so
much. We're going to go ahead. We can
load this up in the Comfy. Uh, that's
supported now. Day one, we had some
issues with the weights, but Comfy
jumped on it like he always does, and
they got that done very quickly. I'm
highly appreciative of the Comfy UI.
We're going to download this, throw it
into the Comfy. Let's see what we can
do. Okay, we have everything loaded up
into Comfy here. So, this is all pretty
much the default workflow currently. Um,
if you come here to templates, they have
it right here. You may have to search
for it depending on when you're looking
at this, but Z image turbo text to
image. We load that up. It's all in a
subgraph. I just expanded it. I added my
Laura loader model only. We have our Z
image turbolure loaded up. Um, I
actually prefer this at eight. That's
what they mention on the page. We can
leave the rest of this the same. I think
res multistep makes it where four works.
I'm going to switch it over to just UER
for now. Uh, this is really big.
You can probably do it that big. We just
didn't train it that big. We won't do
all this wide angle view of a dog flying
a plane in the pilot seat. Let's give it
a run.
Perfect. [laughter]
[gasps]
You know, I mean, everyone tries to make
things that are like way better art than
people can make, but I just love this
little kid stuff. Like, it's not too
much like a plane. It's like a kid would
draw a plane.
All right, let's try something else. A
skateboarder doing a kick flip down a
flight of stairs.
[laughter]
Oh, I just love this. Look at that. Oh,
it's so good. I mean, the these are
actually like kid drawings. It's so I
don't know. I just get warmed up. I'll
do something kind of racy here. A woman
at a strip club. There you guys go. I
mean, screenshot that. Save it for
later. Don't say that I don't go racy
with my content. That gets you
everything you need right there. Look at
that. It's beautiful. Let's go ahead and
give it another run. Men, contain
yourself. Okay, let's see what else we
could do here. We have Christmas coming
up. So, let's do this. Santa holding a
bag of towi. Okay, that mistyped it, but
there we go. Santa holding a bag of
toys. He is flying over the city. And
finally, we have to do one final one. A
horse holding a sign that says, "I
trained this Z image turbolura on AI
toolkit."
And there it is. I just absolutely love
this style.
All right, guys. That's it. That's how
you do it. That's how you train uh Z
image Turbo Laura. If you're trying to
train a character, it works basically
the same way. Don't switch to the high
noise option of doing a character
though. You can just just do it
balanced. You can do time steps of
weighted sigmoid. All that will be the
same. Character lawyers actually train a
lot faster. I may cover that in a video,
too. But this model is not great at
style. It's focused on realism. So, we
took it to the extreme anti-realism
here. So, this is just to show you you
can go this far with it. So, everything
else along the way you can easily do. If
you found this helpful, do what the bear
says. Be sure to like and subscribe.
Click those buttons at the bottom. That
helps me out a ton on YouTube. And
shameless plug time. If you enjoy this
video, you enjoy AI toolkit, you enjoy
my work figuring out how to train a
turbo model and doing all that. I don't
make any money from using my software.
or if you're using it on some service. I
don't make money from that. All of my
money is made from supporters. That's
it. That's how I make my money. So, head
over here to a.com/support.
You can support me on Patreon, GitHub
sponsors, PayPal. You can buy some
merch, get a t-shirt. You can check out
all of the amazing supporters that make
all my work possible. Many of these
people have been supporting me since day
one. like the very first time I was like
begging for money, these people came in
and a lot more people have joined them
along the way and that's what allows me
to do this full-time. I'm finally about
at the point where I'm about making ends
meet and not blowing through my savings
like it's on fire. Thank all of you so
much for donating and please consider
supporting me if you find this helpful.
That's it. I hate begging for money, but
I got to do it. Go make some really cool
Z image lures. I love you guys. I'll see
you next time. Bye. [music]